"The Role of Accountability in Weight Loss"
Among the more radical
weight loss methods
that have been employed:
"therapeutic starvation."
How can you get people
to stop eating?
Wire their jaws shut.
Ugh, yes,
that used to be a thing.
Terrible.
I can't even imagine
the psychological toll.
Surgical fixes
like jaw wiring aside,
what is the most effective
long-term obesity program
ever published
in the medical literature?
The Trevose Behavior
Modification Program.
Named after a town
in Pennsylvania,
the program ran all-volunteer
self-help support groups
beginning in 1970,
offering lifetime treatment
at no cost.
Wait, the most successful
weight loss program
in history was free?
Why haven't more people
heard about it?
Probably because of that:
It was free.
Multimillion dollar corporations
like Weight Watchers
spend hundreds of millions
of dollars
on advertising each year.
How do the two programs compare?
After two years
in Weight Watchers,
the average weight loss
is about six pounds (2.7 kg).
After two years
in the Trevose Program,
the average weight loss
was 39 pounds (17.7 kg),
and after five years,
Trevose participants were
still down 35 pounds (16 kg).
Now, that's only
for about the 20%
who stayed in the program
that long.
What about Weight Watchers
participants?
After five years
sticking with the most rigorous
52-week Weight Watchers program,
participants did maintain
a lower weight—
but only about
five and a half pounds (2.5 kg).
And drop out, when reported,
averaged around 20%.
What appears to be the secret
to the Trevose Program's
success?
Extreme accountability.
The Trevose Program
has been likened
to "weight-loss boot camp,"
but the rigor is in the rules,
not the methods.
The program utilizes
the standard array
of traditional techniques:
calorie cutting, exercise,
weekly weigh-ins,
and group support.
What sets it apart
is the strictness
of its enforcement.
If members fail
to attend meetings
or meet their weight loss goals,
they are immediately kicked out,
and they can never return.
The program accepts
almost anyone
with one critical exception:
no past participants
are allowed.
There are no second chances,
no do-overs, no excuses.
When people sign up,
they understand that this is
a once-in-a-lifetime
opportunity.
Unfortunately,
the program closed in 2021
due to the challenges
of hosting in-person groups
during the COVID-19 pandemic.
Trevose's tough love approach
may not be for everyone,
but key principles for success,
such as social support,
may be universal.
A randomized trial
found that group therapy
tends to produce
greater results
than going it on our own,
even among those
who initially expressed
a preference
for individual treatment.
Similarly, health coaches
can also help people
stay engaged and accountable.
Self-monitoring is
another important takeaway,
considered the "cornerstone"
of behavioral change
for weight loss.
Without awareness
of our progress,
it may be hard
to reach our goals.
There are now high-tech
wearable activity trackers
to monitor our exercise
to facilitate weight loss,
but the best device
for monitoring calorie intake
may be
the humble bathroom scale.
In the past, though,
frequent self-weighing
for weight control
was actively discouraged.
Clinicians were concerned
dieters might be discouraged
by the slow rate
of weight loss,
or worse, suffer
negative psychological effects,
potentially putting one at risk
for depression
or body image issues.
Self-weighing may indeed
have a negative impact
for adolescents and adults
without excess weight,
but daily or weekly
self-weighing
among adults who are overweight
or adults with obesity
appears to actually improve
psychological health
and well-being.
Among those
who need to lose weight,
self-weighing is
broadly positive:
associated with less depression,
disordered eating,
and body dissatisfaction.
But this may be confounded
by the fact
that regular self-weighing
improves weight loss.
Findings from more than a dozen
such prospective studies
have consistently found
regular self-weighing
to be associated
with successful weight loss
and maintenance,
but they are all stricken
with the same nagging question.
It's unknown whether those
who weigh themselves daily
are more motivated
to lose weight
and, therefore, more likely
to weigh themselves
more frequently
or whether frequent
self-weighing
sparks behavior change
that leads to weight loss.
Or maybe there's
a third factor at play.
You can't prove
cause and effect
until you put it to the test.
Randomized controlled trials
have shown
that those assigned
to daily weighing
accompanied
by weekly email messaging
tailored to their progress
lost more weight,
about six percent more.
They were better able
to resist weight gain
and maintained
more weight loss.
The control groups
received nothing, though;
so, it's hard to separate
the effects of the weighing
from the regular contact.
Just telling individuals
with obesity
to weigh themselves each day
without any further instruction
or feedback
is ineffective
as a sole strategy.
Self-monitoring has been shown
to be an effective
behavioral technique
for helping people eat
more healthfully,
exercise more,
and drink less alcohol.
But unlike those cases,
self-weighing is monitoring
an outcome
rather than specific behaviors.
If people don't know
what to do about the fact
they're gaining weight,
it may not help.
Self-weighing is
just a feedback tool
to allow
for personal accountability,
offering positive
or negative reinforcement
for whatever strategies
you've chosen to try out.
The evidence supporting
frequent self-weighing
as a part of weight management
interventions
is now considered so strong
that it's been incorporated
into the official
weight management guidelines
put out by the Obesity Society,
along with the American
Heart Association
and the American College
of Cardiology
and as part
of their most recent guidelines
for the prevention
of heart disease
among people who are overweight
or who have obesity.
So, how often
should we weigh ourselves?
There is insufficient evidence
to support a specific
frequency of weighing,
whether weekly or daily.
One study found
that twice daily—
upon waking
and again right before bed—
appeared superior to once a day,
about six pounds (2.7 kg)
versus two pounds (0.9 kg)
of weight loss
over 12 weeks;
so, that's the frequency
recommended by Dr. Greger
in his book
on evidence-based weight loss,
How Not to Diet.